I was about 10 years old
كنت فى العاشرة من العمر
on a camping trip with my dad
فى رحلة تخييم مع أبي
in the Adirondack Mountains, a wilderness area
فى جبال الاديرونداك وهي منطقة برية
in the northern part of New York State.
فى الجزء الشمالي من ولاية نيويورك.
It was a beautiful day.
لقد كان يوما جميلا
The forest was sparkling.
و كانت الغابة متلئلئة.
The sun made the leaves glow like stained glass,
فسقوط الشمس على الاوراق جعلها تسطع كالزجاج الملون
and if it weren't for the path we were following,
و لو لم يكن موجودة على طريقنا،
we could almost pretend we were
لظننا أنّنا أول بشر
the first human beings to ever walk that land.
تطأ أقدامهم ذلك المكان.
We got to our campsite.
وصلنا إلى مكان التخييم.
It was a lean-to on a bluff
و الذي كان منحدرا
looking over a crystal, beautiful lake,
مطلّا على بحيرة متلألأة جميلة
when I discovered a horror.
و في تلك اللحظة اكتشفت أمرا مروّعا.
Behind the lean-to was a dump,
كانت توجد النفايات خلف المنحدر
maybe 40 feet square
على مساحة 40 قدما مكعّبا (3.7 مترا مكعبا)
with rotting apple cores
مليئة بنوى التفاح المتعفن
and balled-up aluminum foil,
تكوّمت فوقها رقائق الالمنيوم
and a dead sneaker.
و حذاء رياضي قديم.
And I was astonished,
لقد أصابني الذهول
I was very angry, and I was deeply confused.
و كنت غاضبة جدا و مرتبكة للغاية.
The campers who were too lazy
المخيمون كانوا كسولين جدّا لدرجة
to take out what they had brought in,
عدم اخراجهم ما احضروه معهم،
who did they think would clean up after them?
من الذي كانوا يعتقدون انه سياتي لينظف مخلّفاتهم؟
That question stayed with me,
لقد بقي هذا السؤال في ذهني لفترة
and it simplified a little.
لكنه أصبح ابسط.
Who cleans up after us?
فمن الذي ينظف مخلفاتنا؟
However you configure
مهما يكن مكانك
or wherever you place the us,
أو من تكون أنت،
who cleans up after us in Istanbul?
من الذي ينظف مخلفاتنا في اسطنبول؟
Who cleans up after us in Rio
من الذي ينظف مخلفاننا في ريو
or in Paris or in London?
أو باريس أو لندن؟
Here in New York,
هنا فى نيويورك،
the Department of Sanitation cleans up after us,
إدارة الصرف الصحي تقوم بذلك،
to the tune of 11,000 tons of garbage
كميّة تصل إلى 11 ألف طن من القمامة
and 2,000 tons of recyclables every day.
و 2000 طن من المواد المعاد تدويرها يوميا.
I wanted to get to know them as individuals.
أردت ان أتعرف عليهم كأفراد.
I wanted to understand who takes the job.
أردت ان أعرف من يتولى القيام بهذا العمل.
What's it like to wear the uniform
كيفية ارتداء الزيّ
and bear that burden?
و تحمّل هذا العبء.
So I started a research project with them.
لذلك بدأت مشروعا بحثيا معهم،
I rode in the trucks and walked the routes
أستقليت الشاحنات و مشيت فى الطرق
and interviewed people in offices and facilities
و قابت الناس فى المكاتب و المرافق
all over the city,
فى جميع انحاء المدينة،
and I learned a lot,
و تعلمت الكثير
but I was still an outsider.
و لكني كنت ما ازال دخيلة.
I needed to go deeper.
كنت احتاج إلى التّعمق أكثر.
So I took the job as a sanitation worker.
فاشتغلت كعامل صرف صحي.
I didn't just ride in the trucks now. I drove the trucks.
و لم أركب الشاحنات و حسب، بل كنت أقودها.
And I operated the mechanical brooms and I plowed the snow.
قمت بتشغيل ماكينات المكانس الآلية و حرثت الثلج،
It was a remarkable privilege
لقد كان شرفا ملحوظا
and an amazing education.
و مصدر تعليم مدهش.
Everyone asks about the smell.
الجميع يتساءل عن الرائحة،
It's there, but it's not as prevalent as you think,
إنّها موجودة و لكنها ليست بالسوء الذي تعتقدونه،
and on days when it is really bad,
في بعض الأيام عندما تسوء الأمور فعلا،
you get used to it rather quickly.
تستطيع التاقلم مع الأمر بسرعة.
The weight takes a long time to get used to.
أمّا الوزن فيستغرق وقتا طويلا كي تعتاد عليه.
I knew people who were several years on the job
أعرف أشخاصا عملوا لسنوات في هذه الوظيفة
whose bodies were still adjusting to the burden
لكن اجسامهم لا تزال تتاقلم إلى درجة
of bearing on your body
تحمّل جسمك
tons of trash every week.
للاطنان من النفايات كل اسبوع.
Then there's the danger.
ثم هناك الخطر.
According to the Bureau of Labor Statistics,
فطبقا لمكتب لابور للاحصائيات،
sanitation work is one of the 10 most dangerous
العمل فى الصرف الصحي هو واحدة من 10 أخطر
occupations in the country,
المهن فى البلاد،
and I learned why.
و قد فهمت السبب.
You're in and out of traffic all day,
فعليك التحرك باستمرار داخل و خارج حركة المرور،
and it's zooming around you.
و تحيط بك وسائل النّقل.
It just wants to get past you, so it's often
و كلّها ترغب في تجاوزك و في العادة
the motorist is not paying attention.
يكون سائقوا الدراجات النّارية غير حذرين.
That's really bad for the worker.
هذا أمر سيء حقّا للعامل.
And then the garbage itself is full of hazards
ثمّ أنّ القمامة نفسها مليئة بالمواد الخطرة
that often fly back out of the truck
التي غالبا ما تسقط و تتطاير من الشّاحنة
and do terrible harm.
مسبّبة ضررا رهيبا.
I also learned about the relentlessness of trash.
تعلمت أيضا عن قسوة النفايات.
When you step off the curb
فعندما تخطو حافة الرصيف
and you see a city from behind a truck,
وتشاهد المدينة من وراء الشاحنة،
you come to understand that trash
تفهم أنّ القمامة هي في حد ذاتها
is like a force of nature unto itself.
كقوة من قوى الطبيعة.
It never stops coming.
إنّها لا تتوقف أبدا عن المجيء.
It's also like a form of respiration or circulation.
كما انها ايضا كأنها شكل من أشكال التنفس او الدورة الدموية.
It must always be in motion.
عليها أن تكون دوما في حركة.
And then there's the stigma.
وثم هناك وصمة العار.
You put on the uniform, and you become invisible
حالما تضع الزيّ، تصبح غير مرئيّ
until someone is upset with you for whatever reason
إلى أن يصبح شخص ما مستاء منك لسبب ما
like you've blocked traffic with your truck,
كسدّ الطريق على السيارات بشاحنتك،
or you're taking a break too close to their home,
أو أخذ استراحة بجانب منازلهم،
or you're drinking coffee in their diner,
او كنت تشرب القهوة في مقهاهم،
and they will come and scorn you,
سوف يأتون إليك و يسخرون منك،
and tell you that they don't want you anywhere near them.
و يخبرونك بعدم رغبتهم في تواجدك بجانبهم.
I find the stigma especially ironic,
أجد هذا الاحتقار مثيرا للسخرية،
because I strongly believe that sanitation workers
لأنّني أؤمن بشدّة أنّ عاملي النّظافة
are the most important labor force
هي أهمّ قوة عاملة
on the streets of the city, for three reasons.
في شوارع المدينة، لثلاثة أسباب.
They are the first guardians of public health.
إنّهم أول حراس للصحة العمومية.
If they're not taking away trash
إن لم يقوموا بأخذ النّفايات
efficiently and effectively every day,
كما ينبغي بصفة يومية،
it starts to spill out of its containments,
فسوف تفيض من الحاويات
and the dangers inherent to it threaten us
و المشاكل التي قد يسبّبها ذلك
in very real ways.
خطيرة فعلا علينا.
Diseases we've had in check for decades and centuries
الأمراض التي لم تصبنا لعقود و قرون
burst forth again and start to harm us.
سوف تعود و تأذينا مجدّدا.
The economy needs them.
الاقتصاد يحتاج هؤلاء العاملين.
If we can't throw out the old stuff,
لا نستطيع طرد العمال القدماء،
we have no room for the new stuff,
و لا مكان للعمال الجدد عندنا،
so then the engines of the economy
و هكذا فإنّ عجلات الاقتصاد
start to sputter when consumption is compromised.
تبدأ بالدوران عندما يكون الاستهلاك في خطر.
I'm not advocating capitalism, I'm just pointing out their relationship.
أنا لا أدعو إلى الرأسماليّة، أنا فقط أشير إلى العلاقة.
And then there's what I call
وهناك أيضا ما أدعوه
our average, necessary quotidian velocity.
سرعتنا اليومية الأساسية العاديّة.
By that I simply mean
و بذلك أنا أقصد
how fast we're used to moving
مدى السرعة التي نتحرّك بها
in the contemporary day and age.
في يومنا و عصرنا المعاصر.
We usually don't care for, repair, clean, carry around
نحن في العادة لا نهتمّ بالتّصليح و التنظيف و حمل
our coffee cup, our shopping bag,
أكواب قهوتنا أو أكياس التّسوق
our bottle of water.
أو قوارير المياه.
We use them, we throw them out, we forget about them,
نحن نستعملها و نرميها ثمّ ننسى أمرها تماما،
because we know there's a workforce
لأنّنا نعلم أنّ هناك قوة عاملة
on the other side that's going to take it all away.
في الجانب الآخر ستقوم بأخذها بعيدا.
So I want to suggest today a couple of ways
لذلك أنا أرغب اليوم في اقتراح بعض الطّرق
to think about sanitation that will perhaps help
للتّفكير في نّظام الصّرف الصحي بطريقة قد تساعد
ameliorate the stigma
على نزع الوصمة
and bring them into this conversation
و تضمينهم في هذا الحوار
of how to craft a city that is sustainable and humane.
حول كيفيّة جعل المدينة مستدامة و إنسانيّة.
Their work, I think, is kind of liturgical.
عملهم حسب رأيي طقسيّ نوعا ما.
They're on the streets every day, rhythmically.
إنّهم هناك في الشوارع كل يوم، بشكل إيقاعيّ.
They wear a uniform in many cities.
إنّهم يرتدون زيّا في مدن عديدة.
You know when to expect them.
أنت تعلم متى تتوقّع قدومهم.
And their work lets us do our work.
و عملهم يسمح لنا بالقيام بأعمالنا.
They are almost a form of reassurance.
إنّهم تقريبا نوع من الإعادة الطمأنينة.
The flow that they maintain
السريان الذي يحافظون عليه
keeps us safe from ourselves,
يجعلنا آمنين من أنفسنا
from our own dross, our cast-offs,
من نفايات المعادن خاصّتنا،
and that flow must be maintained always
و ذلك السريان عليه أن يبقى متدفّقا دائما
no matter what.
مهما يحصل.
On the day after September 11 in 2001,
في اليوم ما بعد 11 من سبتمبر 2001،
I heard the growl of a sanitation truck on the street,
سمعت هدير شاحنة نفايات في الشّارع،
and I grabbed my infant son and I ran downstairs
و أمسكت بطفلي الصغير و ركضت إلى الطابق السفلي
and there was a man doing his paper recycling route
و كان هناك رجل يقوم بجمع نفايات الأوراق
like he did every Wednesday.
كما كان يفعل كلّ يوم أربعاء.
And I tried to thank him for doing his work
حاولت أن أشكره لقيامه بعمله
on that day of all days,
في ذلك اليوم بالذّات،
but I started to cry.
لكنني بدأت بالبكاء.
And he looked at me,
و نظر إليّ
and he just nodded, and he said,
و أومأ برأسه و قال
"We're going to be okay.
"سوف نكون على ما يرام.
We're going to be okay."
سوف نكون على ما يرام."
It was a little while later that I started
بعد وقت قصير من تلك الحادثة، بدأت
my research with sanitation,
ببحثي حول نظام الصرف الصحيّ
and I met that man again.
و قابلت ذلك الرّجل مجدّدا.
His name is Paulie, and we worked together many times,
كان اسمه بولي و عملنا معا عديد المرات،
and we became good friends.
و أصبحنا أصدقاء جيّدين.
I want to believe that Paulie was right.
أرغب في الاعتقاد أنّ بولي كان محقّا.
We are going to be okay.
أنّنا سوف نكون على ما يرام.
But in our effort to reconfigure
لكن في مجهودنا في محاولة إعادة تكوين
how we as a species exist on this planet,
كيفيّة عيش جنسنا على هذا الكوكب
we must include and take account of
علينا إضافة التكاليف و أخذها بعين الاعتبار
all the costs, including the very real human cost
منها تكلفة العمل التي يقوم بها الكائن البشريّ
of the labor.
نفسه.
And we also would be well informed
كما ينبغي أن نكون على دراية
to reach out to the people who do that work
للتواصل مع هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين يقومون بذلك العمل
and get their expertise
و كسب خبراتهم
on how do we think about,
عن كيفية تفكيرنا
how do we create systems around sustainability
و كيفية صنعنا لأنظمة مستديمة
that perhaps take us from curbside recycling,
التي تأخذنا من اعادة تدوير الرّصيف
which is a remarkable success across 40 years,
الذي كانت ناجحا طيلة 40 سنة
across the United States and countries around the world,
في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية و مختلف البلدان حول العالم
and lift us up to a broader horizon
و حملنا إلى أفق أوسع
where we're looking at other forms of waste
حيث هناك أشكال أخرى من القمامة
that could be lessened
يمكن تقليلها
from manufacturing and industrial sources.
من قبل المصادر المصنّعة.
Municipal waste, what we think of when we talk about garbage,
النّفايات الإداريّة، ما نفكّر فيه عند حديثنا عن القمامة،
accounts for three percent of the nation's waste stream.
يشكّل 3% من مجموع النّفايات بالبلد.
It's a remarkable statistic.
إنّها احصائية مثيرة للاهتمام.
So in the flow of your days,
إذن فأثناء مضي أيّامنا،
in the flow of your lives,
و أثناء حيواتنا،
next time you see someone whose job is
عندم ترون في المرة المقبلة شخصا
to clean up after you,
عمله جمع قمامتك،
take a moment to acknowledge them.
خذ لحظة من وقتك لشكره .
Take a moment to say thank you.
خذ دقيقة لتقول فيها شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)